Guide to the Darrin Zammit Lupi photojournalism archive, 2004-2017 RL.11613
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Malta Detention, 2004-2013; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 box 20 photographic prints; 12.57 Gigabytes 1821 files (147 tiff, 1646 jpeg, 20 png, 8 pdf)
  - TIFF images (electronic files), 2004-2013; 147 files (.tif); 12 GB
    - Taking out the trash (2), 2008 July 15; Original file id: _JM97917 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0137)
      African would-be immigrants carry a garbage can into a yard in an enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta July 15, 2008. Around 1,500 illegal immigrants are currently held in detention in Malta for periods of up to 18 months. Though their intention was to reach Italy, most found themselves in Malta when they were rescued by the Maltese Armed Forces when they found themselves in difficulties while on their way to reach European soil from Africa. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Playing soccer, 2008 July 15; Original file id: _C4W1529 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0138)
      African would-be immigrants play soccer in an enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta July 15, 2008. Around 1,500 illegal immigrants are currently held in detention in Malta for periods of up to 18 months. Though their intention was to reach Italy, most found themselves in Malta when they were rescued by the Maltese Armed Forces when they found themselves in difficulties while on their way to reach European soil from Africa. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Soldier outside the perimeter fence, 2008 July 15; Original file id: _C4W1547 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0139)
      An Armed Forces of Malta soldier walks past the perimeter fence surrounding an enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta July 15, 2008. Around 1,500 illegal immigrants are currently held in detention in Malta for periods of up to 18 months. Though their intention was to reach Italy, most found themselves in Malta when they were rescued by the Maltese Armed Forces when they found themselves in difficulties while on their way to reach European soil from Africa. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Feet up, 2008 July 15; Original file id: _C4W1561 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0140)
      African would-be immigrants put their feet up against a perimeter fence in an enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta July 15, 2008. Around 1,500 illegal immigrants are currently held in detention in Malta for periods of up to 18 months. Though their intention was to reach Italy, most found themselves in Malta when they were rescued by the Maltese Armed Forces when they found themselves in difficulties while on their way to reach European soil from Africa. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - "Peace and Life … not Prison", 2009 January 10; Original file id: _JM99919 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0141)
      Somali would-be immigrants hold a protest at being held in detention at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta January 10, 2009. The would-be immigrants had been rescued by the Armed Forces of Malta after finding themselves in difficulty while on their way to reach European soil from Africa. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Aerial view of Safi detention centre (1), 2009 March 13; Original file id: _JM96554 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0142)
      The Safi detention centre is seen in Safi outside Valletta March 13, 2009. International aid agency Medecins Sans Frontieres said on Friday it has suspended operations at Malta's migrant detention centres, citing appalling living conditions. European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot is expected to visit a detention centre on Saturday. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Aerial view of Safi detention centre (2), 2009 March 13; Original file id: _JM96586 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0143)
      Would-be immigrants walk in the yard of the Safi detention centre outside Valletta March 13, 2009. International aid agency Medecins Sans Frontieres said on Friday it has suspended operations at Malta's migrant detention centres, citing appalling living conditions. European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot is expected to visit a detention centre on Saturday. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot visits detention camp (1), 2009 March 14; Original file id: _MG_3188 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0144)
      European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (3rd L) visits the Lyster Detention Centre for illegal immigrants in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot visits detention camp (2), 2009 March 14; Original file id: _MG_3253 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0145)
      European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (3rd R) talks to illegal immigrants at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Hand on fence, 2009 March 14; Original file id: _JM96757 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0146)
      An illegal immigrant holds onto a perimeter fence during a fact-finding visit by European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (not pictured) at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Spontaneous protest (1), 2009 March 14; Original file id: _JM96776 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0147)
      Illegal immigrants hold a spontaneous protest during a fact-finding visit by European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (not pictured) at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Spontaneous protest (2), 2009 March 14; Original file id: _MG_3338 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0148)
    - Peeking Out, 2009 March 14; Original file id: _JM96809 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0149)
      A West African illegal immigrant pokes his head out of his room during a fact-finding visit by European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (not pictured) at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - West African immigrant outside his room, 2009 March 14; Original file id: _MG_3391 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0150)
      A West African illegal immigrant stands outside his room during a fact-finding visit by European Justice Commissioner Jacques Barrot (not pictured) at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, March 14, 2009. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Central staircase, 2010 April 15; Original file id: _MG_7147 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0151)
      An Armed Forces of Malta soldier walks through the Lyster Barracks detention centre for irregular immigrants in Hal Far, outside Valletta, April 15, 2010. The currently empty centre is undergoing extensive refurbishment in the event that immigrants trying to reach Europe from Africa start landing in Malta as summer approaches, as has happened over the past few years. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Friendly tease, 2011 April 19; Original file id: _MG_3125 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0152)
      An Ethiopian immigrant sticks his tongue out at a child carried by his father at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, April 19, 2011. Around 1,100 African immigrants fleeing the violence in Libya have arrived in Malta over the past month, according to officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Child picks food off the floor, 2011 April 19; Original file id: _MG_3098 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0153)
      An African immigrant child picks up a piece of food from the floor as Maltese soldiers walk by at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta April 19, 2011. Around 1,100 African immigrants fleeing the violence in Libya have arrived in Malta over the past month, according to officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Baby behind bars, 2011 April 19; Original file id: _MG_3170 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0154)
      An Ethiopian immigrant carries her two-week old child at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta April 19, 2011. Around 1,100 African immigrants fleeing the violence in Libya have arrived in Malta over the past month, according to officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Child plays with ball, 2011 April 19; Original file id: _MG_3206 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0155)
      African immigrant children play with a ball at the Lyster Detention Centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta April 19, 2011. Around 1,100 African immigrants fleeing the violence in Libya have arrived in Malta over the past month, according to officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Court arraignment after riot (1), 2011 August 17; Original file id: _JM98543 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0156)
      Handcuffed African irregular immigrants walk out of a court in Valletta August 17, 2011. Twenty-three immigrants were charged with starting a riot, causing damage and injuring police officers in a disturbance at a detention camp on Tuesday. The immigrants, who all arrived from Libya over the last six months, rioted after being told that their request for humanitarian protection had been refused, according to local media. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Court arraignment after riot (2), 2011 August 17; Original file id: _JM98568 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0157)
      An African irregular immigrant points at a head injury while sitting in a police bus outside a court in Valletta August 17, 2011. Twenty-three immigrants were charged with starting a riot, causing damage and injuring police officers in a disturbance at a detention camp on Tuesday. The immigrants, who all arrived from Libya over the last six months, rioted after being told that their request for humanitarian protection had been refused, according to local media. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Court arraignment after riot (3), 2011 August 17; Original file id: _JM98606 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0158)
      African irregular immigrants sit in a police bus outside a court in Valletta August 17, 2011. Twenty-three immigrants were charged with starting a riot, causing damage and injuring police officers in a disturbance at a detention camp on Tuesday. The immigrants, who all arrived from Libya over the last six months, rioted after being told that their request for humanitarian protection had been refused, according to local media. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Barred windows, 2011 October 18; Original file id: _JM94855 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0159)
      Sub-Saharan African irregular immigrants look through barred windows at the Safi detention centre outside Valletta October 18, 2011. According to an analysis by the European Union border control agency Frontex, the Libyan conflict has had a negative effect on Malta in terms of migration. Malta has been warned to expect high numbers of irregular immigrants to continue to flow out of Libya as the new government there remains focused on other priorities, local media reported. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Looking through the fence, 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90007 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0160)
      A Somali immigrant looks through a fence as others play soccer behind him at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Monthly hygienic items allowance, 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM99127 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0161)
      A chart showing the monthly hygienic items each immigrant is entitled to is seen outside the showers at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, January 20, 2012. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - TV room (2), 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90063 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0162)
      Somali immigrants watch television in the common room at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Medication distribution (1), 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90084 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0163)
      A nurse (2nd R) distributes medication to Somali immigrants at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Medication distribution (2), 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90101 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0164)
      A nurse distributes medication to Somali immigrants at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Fighting off the cold, 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90117 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0165)
      Somali immigrants wrap themselves in blankets in the common room at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Blanket receipts, 2012 January 20; Original file id: _JM90145 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0166)
      A Detention Service officer (C) sorts out receipts for blankets distributed to Somali immigrants in the common room at the Lyster Barracks detention centre in Hal Far, outside Valletta, January 20, 2012. 68 Somali immigrants who were rescued while fleeing from Libya on January 15 are being held in the camp by Maltese authorities while their requests for humanitarian protection are processed, government officials said. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Justice for Mamadou Kamara, 2012 July 11; Original file id: _MG_3514 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0167)
      African immigrants hold posters showing Mamadou Kamara of Mali, who was killed while being held in detention by Maltese authorities during a demonstration against racism, in Valletta July 11, 2012. Two soldiers, who stand accused of murdering the Mali immigrant in a Detention Service van in June, were granted bail by the court earlier this week after hearing two days of evidence, according to local media. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Food distribution, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4399 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0168)
      An African illegal immigrant helps with the food distribution at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Playing board games, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4402 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0169)
      African illegal immigrants play a board game in their enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Boredom, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4411 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0170)
      African illegal immigrants mill around at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - On the window ledge, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97231 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0171)
      African illegal immigrants sit on a window ledge at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Red curtain, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4454 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0172)
      An African illegal immigrant stands next to his bed at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Talking near beds, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97259 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0173)
    - Looking towards the light, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4514 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0174)
    - Holy pictures (1), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97300 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0175)
      African illegal immigrants talk in front of Christian holy pictures on a wall in their enclosed compound at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Dhuhr (noon) prayers at Safi detention centre (1), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97312 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0176)
      Muslim illegal immigrants take part in midday prayers at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Dhuhr (noon) prayers at Safi detention centre (2), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4536 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0177)
    - Dhuhr (noon) prayers at Safi detention centre (3), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97338 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0178)
    - Dhuhr (noon) prayers at Safi dention centre (4), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4550 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0179)
    - Dhuhr (noon) prayers at Safi detention centre (5), 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4554 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0180)
    - Calling home, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97342 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0181)
      An African illegal immigrant sits on a window ledge while talking on the telephone at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - English language lessons, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _MG_4575 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0182)
      African illegal immigrants attend an English language lesson at the Safi detention centre in Safi, outside Valletta, July 17, 2012. Illegal immigrants arriving on the island of Malta are detained for up to 18 months, a policy which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) has said urgently needs a comprehensive review following the death of a Malian immigrant while in custody last month, according to local media. There are currently around 1000 immigrants being held in detention, according to government officials. Photo: Darrin Zammit Lupi
    - Hands and feet out, 2012 July 17; Original file id: _JM97371 (Digital-materials RL11613-SET-0005, Image-file RL.11613-TIFF-0183)